foreign
um
[Music]
hello everybody welcome to episode 52 of
the ask a visit show
as you know tonight today wherever you
are uh today is a live video chat
episode which means i'm going to be
taking live video chat
questions from all of you
the link for joining the video chat is
on top of the chat box
unfortunately only 10 people can join at
the time and right now i can see that
the room is full so okay so keep trying
those of you who want to join
and the rules are very simple there are
three topics three very broad topics
history geopolitics and
science
and i am going to be taking one question
per person
so last week also i had said one
question per person but then i took many
questions for people per person so this
time i want uh more people to get the
chance to be on the show so i'm going to
take only one question
per person all right so that's the very
simple basic rules
so
uh
let me first see who all is there with
us
and
lots and lots and lots of people so nice
to see you all always a great honor that
you all join my live broadcast always
very grateful to all of you good evening
and good day to all of you wherever you
are
all right let's get into the questions
and i can see there are a number of
people waiting to join
uh
the broadcast so let us start with
pranav patil
hello pranav how are you doing
i'm fine sir how are you
i'm very well where are you from
i am from bangladesh
very nice nice so nice to see you so
what's your question
sir my question is that
can you suggest books about the islamic
invasion of india since
there's a lot you tell a lot about it
but we want to know the sources
see i haven't read one book or two books
or something i have read i've been
reading books since since i was like
before i was 10 years old so
unfortunately the the problem is that uh
when it comes to the islamic or turkic
invasions of india very few people have
written
a proper book i mean you will
unfortunately not find a single book
that deals with this specific topic so
what i have done is i have read lots of
books hundreds of books i've read
thousands of research papers and
articles and all that magazine articles
and research articles so that's how i
i've got my information my knowledge i
wish i could refer i could suggest one
book or three books to you but it's not
going to be possible because there is no
such thing so if you want to learn about
this you're going to have to do your due
diligence you're going to have to troll
the internet for articles you're going
to have to read books i mean
i can't think of a single book that
deals with this topic you see that's the
unfortunate thing i i really appreciate
that you are interested in this
particular uh portion of our history it
is a very important phase one that has
been completely neglected by historians
deliberately of course
so i apologize that i am unable to give
you a single book or two books what i
would suggest is that you're very young
i really like that
so you know what you've got an entire
lifetime ahead of you so whenever you
get some free time do some research do
some original research of your own do
some reading the internet today contains
all the sources of information and
knowledge that we can hope for and most
of it is if you know where to look it's
available for free so so spend some time
research things read as much as you can
and i think you will get more
information from the internet than
actually from various textbooks so
that's what i can say sir
thank you very much for your question
very nice seeing you very nice seeing
you
all right thank you
most welcome all the best bye bye
okay who else shall we take let us take
okay
hi rochit good evening good day hello
sir good evening
sir yes can you please
yes one of the one of the greatest
dramatists of all time of in human
history so kalidas has written i mean we
don't quite know when kali does lived
because as you know all our sources of
information have disappeared they've
been wiped out
he
i believe he wrote his plays in
classical sanskrit
uh what are the names of the plays
was it
no i think there is one called bhas and
there is one called kalidas so there are
two of these
so i i can't give you the exact names of
the plays at all but he's one of the
greatest
dramatists and writers of classical
sanskrit um very interesting plays that
he has written that have been
part of our
lore for a very long time so if you know
what as right now i cannot think of the
exact names of those plays and all that
off the top of my head but you have
suggested a very interesting topic
actually kalidas is a very very uh
important part of our literary history
so what i can do
is in the future i'll make a video about
about kalidas and the plays that he
wrote and his impact
on
our cultural history our literary
history and possibly in the history in
the in the literary scene worldwide
actually so that's what i can do in the
future right now i can't think of the
specific details about kalidas so that's
what i can say right now so my great
grandfather
[Music]
is it available on amazon or flipkart or
something yes
awesome awesome that's great i shall try
and find the book and thank you for the
reference i would
request all the viewers to take that as
a reference for kalidas thank you so
much you bye
okay who else shall we bring in
okay let us bring in mr i mr i good
evening
hello
sir i'm a very big fan of you said i hi
i can't very nice to meet you
yes so what's your name where are you
from
my name is actually my name real name is
ishaan and i'm from i actually used to
write
a few comic strips and there was a
detective character called mr eyes
yeah so i'm from chennai
all right what's the question very nice
very nice what's your question yeah
actually i have a lot of bottom of
questions but i can only ask one
question sir can you please talk about
saladin
a yubi yes saladin he is considered to
be one of the greatest heroes of the
islamic world
so salahuddin ayubi was born i think
somewhere in the
i don't remember syria was it
yeah so he was born in the middle east
he is known his exploits uh that are so
famous are about uh fighting of the
european crusaders who wanted to retake
jerusalem
and the so-called holy land which is the
original uh uh homeland of the jews and
it is considered to be the birthplace of
the abrahamic religions of christianity
and jerusalem is the holiest
city of the jews and it is also a very
holy place in christianity so the
crusaders
uh there were a number of crusades that
came in from europe into uh the middle
east and the objective was to retake the
holy land and jerusalem and so on and
they actually succeeded from uh at
certain points in time so salah you be
his his main exploits were to repulse
the crusaders and to
give them the final defeat
which essentially ended the european
rule over the middle east
so
he was born in i believe an aristocratic
kind of family his father was a governor
of sorts of some small town or something
right
and he rose to prominence because of his
brilliance because he was very capable
as a military commander and all that
and he eventually became the king of
egypt you know he became the sultan of
egypt de facto i mean he was supposed to
be the governor of egypt but he became
so powerfully raised in the army he
rebuilt the the city of cairo and so on
was it was it cairo was it alexandria
what are these
yeah right it had been destroyed in
warfare and all that so he rebuilt that
he built an enormous army and he became
more powerful than his overlord and
eventually he got involved in the
resistance to the crusades and he was
able to prevail there as well
and he is uh treated as a hero because
of his alleged chivalry because he was
very uh gracious even towards his
enemies
and so on so that's a little bit of
about saladin i think there are a few
books about him
and so so yeah that's that is the
the role of saladin in history uh
so you know what the the
there are people who want to glorify the
turks and all i think saladin i think
was a kurd he
this is a person who should really be
glorified
i am saying that in in case they want to
find an islamic hero they should look up
to saladin because he actually had many
significant achievements uh right now
the turks are trying to uh to valorize
this guy called jalaluddin
who was a total loser i mean there is
this uh turkey there is this turkish
cereal called
something
yes so now they're also trying to do the
same for jalal deen harasby who lost
anonymously to chinggis khan and who was
the last king of his dynasty he presided
over the dissolution and destruction of
his dynasty and the turks are trying to
valorize him and turn him into some sort
of history some sort of hero so what i
would recommend is that if you want a
hero in your in your in the islamic
world they should look up to saladin not
jalal so so good question sir good
question yeah yeah yeah sir actually i
actually like his one of his quotes i
don't remember it fully but it goes like
don't get in the habit of spilling blood
for blood does not sleep i can't
remember the full quote there are two
three lines before
they don't get the habit but i can't
exactly remember it
it's been frustrating it was against the
crusaders who were
you know raiding the caravans through
the middle east and disturbing the hajj
to if i'm not running mecca
right
all right sir very nice to meet you
great question
one question
yeah so just yeah just one kind requests
up
can you in the future someday can you
make a video on
the iron chancellor the so-called iron
chancellor of germany ottowan bismarck
very good topic i shall definitely put
it on my to-do list
all right thank you so much thank you so
much nice to meet you bye good night
all right who else shall we bring in
who else shall we bring in uh
let us bring in
parama hi parama
hi sir thanks for choosing me again
yeah have you been here before okay you
have yeah right yeah this is my second
time i already you know participated in
your slide
you got really lucky yeah
yeah yeah yeah
yeah so i have uh you know i have a long
question today i have to read it out so
please
yeah yeah so the my question is like why
history has two sides like uh left
history and right history like nowadays
this has become political like my point
is like is this just political or you
know um is this opinion it's like for
example some people say that marat has
did invade west bengal and created a lot
of trouble and some people say that what
whatever they did it was for a noble act
and it was for a nobel course so my
question is like what is this thing
because the history is just one fact how
can it have two sides like completely
two different sides
so yeah good question very good question
so what i would say is that see history
is all written by individuals every
individual has a certain bias a certain
perspective that is shaped by their
environment their upbringing their
worldview their beliefs their religion
the culture and so on and by the by
their shared experiences their lived
experiences and all that so every
individual has a certain bias
and every historian has a certain bias
and of late history has been weaponized
history has been turned into a
propaganda art kind of kind of thing so
what napoleon said is that history is a
set of lies agreed upon the ones who win
the wars and who are the winners they
get to write the history and therefore
we always see these biased accounts
unfortunately in the past two thousand
ten thousand years of human existence we
did not have video cameras audio
equipment so we were not able to record
anything so the only sources we have
accounts of those who wrote history and
the accounts that survived in our case
in india we had these enormous accounts
of history which were all burned in the
destruction of our universities and
libraries and that's why we lost it now
when it comes to the example that you
gave the marathas
these lies have been repeated thousands
of times they are repeated thousands of
times every year in the in the textbooks
in the school in the classrooms and all
so the children they grow up believing
this that this is our history that the
marathas raided us and they destroyed
bengal and they burned everything and
there is this alleged poem that our
mothers used to sing and so on the
bengalis believed that they had this
enormous
tradition of
sati ten thousand plus cases of sati
every year in bengal which is after lies
which is all propaganda again but if you
repeat this thousands of time to times
to a child who is growing up they are
gonna end up believing it and i don't
blame them for it you see i don't blame
the people who believe all this
propaganda because they have grown up
since their very beginning of life
believing all this
being taught all this by their teachers
and that that's the thing so the main
thing is that history and news as well
have have become propaganda tools you
have political policy uh historians have
traditionally been uh
paid for by either the state or by
certain political parties and the same
goes for news organizations until
recently we used to think news is the
most unbiased thing in the world today
we find the new things in various
flavors
flavors various political flavors and so
does history
so that's the thing so we have to be
very careful about what we believe now
that we have kind of grown up so we
should be aware acutely aware of the
fact that everything is potentially
flawed and propaganda you know so that's
what i would say but if this is the
truth then i my question when it comes
to west bengal there like there are a
lot of things that we have learned from
the childhood like for example sati and
you know um
uh how raja ram mohan roy has stopped it
and then there was child marriage and
everything so my question like was
everything was simply a lie because like
all my
childhood we have learned these things
you know this was our history
so like now at this point of time we
have to all unlearn whatever things we
have learned at the past
i agree i mean i there was a point in my
life when i realized everything i have
learned is a lie
i mean everything we have learned in the
textbooks most of it turned out to be
lies because when you look beyond the
textbooks when you look at the research
papers actual factual data and all we
find a whole different story that
actually stares us in the face so it is
all about
are we willing to accept the fact that
all our mental conditioning has been has
been a lie and we need to re uh learn
how to think again learn what to believe
again or are we going to just be
comfortable and say make which means i
will not go into anything i will not
believe anything new i'm just
comfortable believing what i've always
believed it's about are we willing to
grow or are we or do we are we just
comfortable believing what we believe
that's all so i think most of us
have the capability to to unlearn
relearn and to grow as individuals so
that is what i would exhort everybody to
do because you know what it is
unfortunately true that everything we
have been taught most of it has been
nice
that's true but so now like currently
right now if i say like this is the
history this is the original history and
some other people say that that is the
original history people immediately
label them as rightist or leftist this
is something that i really hate like if
you're speaking something like this
people will tell you you are this and if
i'm speaking like that people will tell
you that you're this
welcome to the world i see i face this
every day people
people label me under all kinds of
categories you know
there's nothing see there's nothing you
can do to control the actions of others
what you can do is you decide what to do
with your life that's it so live your
best life and forget about what others
are saying people will talk
right that's how yeah yeah yeah
absolutely absolutely
all right param a wonderful question
nice meeting you again
all right
bye
all right let's take some more questions
that was a wonderful question by parama
let me bring in pranav patil
hello pranav patil are you oh you you
already asked the question sorry sorry
yes
okay i'm gonna i'm gonna sorry okay i'll
get somebody else thank you
okay let us bring in shikhar
shikhar hi yes uh hello and good evening
sir
so where are you from chikar
sir i am from mirzapur it's in up
all right and what's your question sir
so my question is i'm really sorry but
it's very synonymous to what parma asked
that whenever we like in today's time
the one of the main sources for in our
information is internet and whenever we
read about any event or any topic on the
internet we find very opinionated and
biased individuals who are very firm
about their views
so just how to filter whatever we read
or how to like
like how to filter it and whenever we
look at any political event or any event
like today's very hot topic is the aryan
khan and all that case so how to locate
it from an unbiased eye when everybody
is so opinionated about it
all right let me tell you how to do that
ignore people's words ignore people's
opinions just go straight for the facts
it's called first principle thinking
first principle thinking is in
opposition to dogmatic thinking dogmatic
thinking means you are believing you are
you are relying upon the opinions and
words of other people that is one way of
thinking okay something has happened
what do i do how do i form an opinion i
will go and see my favorite three
vloggers i will look and i will go and
see my favorite three news channels and
i will
read my favorite three bloggers and on
the basis of these people's opinions i
will form my own opinion that is that is
called dogmatic thinking first principle
thinking means you go to the actual
source of the facts what has happened
let's talk about for example ca
everybody is against ca and everybody is
against the farm laws so one way of
looking at it is to look at other
people's opinions about caa and the farm
laws the other thing is to use your own
intelligence read the actual law what is
written in the law
and then based on what the government on
the bill that has been passed what has
been written in the law you use your own
intelligence which you have been blessed
with we are all blessed with
intelligence use your own intelligence
your own intellect and use your own
sense of judgment
to power through
the words in the in the law in the bill
which is available for free online it's
available to all of us
and based on that you form your own
opinion instead of relying on the
opinions of others that's the simple way
of of not falling prey to all kinds of
misinformation and propaganda right
unfortunately and you know what the
problem is that our education system
tells you to do the opposite it tells
you to believe what the teachers are
teaching you
and it tells you to believe what is it
in the textbooks and don't look anywhere
else
because you are supposed to memorize the
textbook and reproduce it in the exams
and you're supposed to unquestioningly
blindly obediently believe your teacher
and that is what we go through for year
after year for almost two decades and
that's why we end up in this mental
state that we just look for information
in what others are saying instead of
looking for the actual sources of
information okay so so that is the way
to ensure that you uh
don't fall prey to propaganda and
misinformation
absolutely rely and trust on your own
wisdom and intelligence we are all
intelligent enough but we our education
system makes us believe that we are not
intelligent
so
learn to trust yourself learn to trust
your intelligence and look for the
actual sources of information
all right thank you sir
thank you so much wonderful question all
right i'll see you next time hopefully
all right thanks
all right
let me bring in somebody else
let me bring in somebody
else
we have yesh
very nice what's your question sir yes
sir this is first of all i'm a very very
big fan of your sir you are doing a
great great work for just
realizing us indians that what what we
were and what we have become what is our
potential what we could do in future so
yeah should i ask my question
am i audible to you yes i can hear you
please ask a question yes sir so my
question is like like currently we are
seeing uh in the world of geopolitics uh
you said in previous video that we are
in a stage in the world uh like the
1930s
the world is at the stage of
realignments the countries the global
powers right and there are many uh
you know
uh factors which could uh play a very
significant significant role in uh
somebody's interest like afghanistan
like taiwan's thing is going on
so russia and china currently are
on the same page right
and india's relation with russia are
still warm and we are all we are doing
great deals with them but uh you know
that soviet era thing is missing
right and we are uh india is getting
involved and indulged in the west like
the us we are doing exercises we are
buying some great stuff like apaches
chinooks right and c-17 globe masters we
are indulging with the west we are
we are uh more cooperating with the west
we are
doing deals we are
we are in quad now although it's not a
military uh alliance but yeah we are
engaging with them so what is your your
what is your thought on this like uh is
u.s now a trustable ally because you
said
i know what the us is like we all know
what the us is uh
so the world is uh on the stage of
realignments so what is your thought
that from here where we could go what
will be the future
that's a very interesting and very long
question but okay see so here is i'm
very sorry
sorry no no no no no perfectly fine so
or the thing is that the world is always
in a state of flux the world is all ever
changing
geopolitical uh equations are always in
a state of real real alignment but right
now more than before the world is
changing this seems to be the decade in
which a lot of change is going to happen
so what does india need to do can we
trust the u.s no we cannot trust the u.s
but we can trust them to follow their
national interest
there is no trust in geopolitics there
is no friendship in geopolitics there is
no like or dislike in geopolitics i have
a certain interest my country has a
certain interest long-term interest
the other country has a certain
long-term national interest of their own
what you can do is analyze in detail
what their long-term geopolitical and
national interests are you understand
what your interests are and then you see
if there is any area of convergence
either temporary or long term and then
you play then you act according to those
alignments and convergences potential
convergences
so right now the us and in
india our interests
certainly converge because we are both
concerned about the
incredibly aggressive
and
militaristic rise of china and the kind
of actions they are taking the us
doesn't want the chinese to become a
superpower right india doesn't want
china to become too powerful and too
aggressive and because the chinese have
interest on indian territory and so on
the chinese are they don't want india to
to be a powerful country because it is a
threat to them and so on so forth so
currently our interests are
aligned right now the russians and the
chinese their interests align to a
certain extent they have a very fraught
history and the russians and chinese do
have nuclear missiles pointed at each
other yes so it's always a complex thing
what i would say is that this current
decade is going to be a decade of great
change what we do in this decade is
going to shape our long-term future
because india has two choices either we
become powerful on our own economically
and militarily or will forever going to
have to rely on other countries and
that's not always going to be available
to us yes so it's a decade of change it
is india's choice what india wants to do
we have all the potential in this
in the world we have a very young
intelligent population the most talented
people in the world we have all the
resources in the world
we are a superpower and waiting if we do
the right moves then in the next 10 20
years we can be a middle-income country
gdp per capita overall gdp could exceed
10 trillion 15 trillion if we do the
right things then we could have a
military strength commensurate with that
so it's all up to our leadership what
steps they take whether they make
certain mistakes or they avoid those
mistakes and go in the right direction
right so that's the future it all
depends on these factors
all right
yes
thank you so much for the question thank
you thank you thank you so much
okay let's bring in some other people
who else do we have
who wants to come in okay a.g wants to
come in
hello a.g good evening
good evening sir
nice to meet you where are you from
i'm from maharashtra
i'm from okay what's your question very
nice very nice it's okay what's your
question i got a bunch of them i got a
bunch of them one you said one
one one per person yes yes
the main one what was the metric systems
before the brits or the so-called
mughals in india
[Music]
what was the which system the metric
system
yes
the metric system is a very recent thing
it is something that was brought in
after uh post the development of the
imperial system of units the imperial
system of units is the foot the pound
and all that the yard
and the gallon so that is a system
that's called the imperial system it's a
it's something the british derived on
their own uh it developed in england
it's a british system uh the newest one
the metric system is the kilometer the
centimeter uh
the kilogram and and so on and so forth
that's the metric system
latest most scientific system that's the
one that's in vogue everywhere in india
we had our own systems of units i don't
know what the noise is
i'm gonna have to mute you all right
yeah okay i'm muted this is fine okay so
the system in india was we had our own
system in the past uh
we had
a system i i don't know what the system
itself was called
we had us
the unit of weight we had a number of
units of weight one was called the mana
the mon was a unit of weight we had the
tola in in terms when it came to
measuring the weights of precious metals
i believe
and uh
yeah so we have these systems and these
have been wiped out even during the
indus
era the sindhu saraswati era of our
civilization we had we can see that
there is this standardization of weights
and measures whether you go to harappa
or mohenjodaro or kalimangan or lakigari
or virana or anywhere else you find the
same
system of weights and measures it was
standardized across an enormous
geographical region which says that we
have the same culture the same
civilization and the same system of
units and all that now we don't know
what it was called but it was very much
standardized and that is the reason why
our ancestors were able to create this
enormous highly sophisticated highly
advanced urban civilization over such a
large uh amount of uh land
so that's what so that's what we had it
is something that needs to be researched
i don't know what the system was called
it was the invoked more than 5000 years
ago right so we have always had to
google it
yeah yeah it's not available there's no
information available because our
researchers have been sleeping for the
past many decades we have not done any
research about this but it is there it's
tearing us in the face we have all these
systems of weights and measures the
standard weights and measures throughout
this this geography we don't know what
it was called but it was very
sophisticated it was very precise as
well very small weights up all the way
up to very large weights and all that so
it's it's there we always had this thing
and it is the characteristic of a highly
developed and highly advanced
scientifically and technologically
advanced civilization so that's what we
had
good question sure
so i got two things i got two things
i hope i hope you meet you uh i hope you
meet you i hope i meet you in person
someday
and just video on time
deep deep explanation about time
sure i will put that on my potential
to-do list thank you so much thank you
thank you
sir thank you bye
okay who else let me bring in
apparatchit hi good evening
hello sir
am i horrible
you are audrey
i'm from telangana i came last time i
think you know sir
okay wonderful what's your question for
today
first of all hello sir
hello
[Music]
my question is i wrote some questions so
i'll only ask one
yes
sir in previous time you in previous
podcast you told that
in politics you have to do certain
agenda
like
i'm unable to answer
go ahead go ahead don't be nervous go
ahead
ah political politicians need to create
some
victimhood in order to get the power
like to win seats
and for that they tell the lies
like you know tamil party they say we
are the dravidians
and they convert the people of hindus in
order to win the seats so why don't they
just tell the truth and win the seas
and
they can win the seats
by guys by saying we are the one
civilization
no discrimination of hindu and muslims
like that
why don't they just tell the truth and
win the seats
right right good question good question
so if i was a politician which i won't
be but i if i was a politician i would
not lie but unfortunately the politics
this this business it's a business
actually it's a cutthroat business uh
you have to find every advantage you can
over the other party and so on so the
easiest way
to win votes is to create a sense of
discrimination alienation operation
subjugation and then said that we are
the ones who are going to save you we
are going to tell you the real truth
that you have all been oppressed for
5000 years by this white skinned aryans
and so on and so forth that's why we are
going to save you we are the dravidian
party we are all dravidians we should
stick together blah blah blah blah blah
and that's how they win votes this is
standard uh
there's a standard strategies and
tactics in politics the worldwide not
just in india and so that's what they
are pursuing the so so it's kind of like
geopolitics there's no right or wrong
they will just do whatever they can to
cling to power to win power and to stay
in power and lying is very much power
for the course in politics i would say
that more than 90 more than 99 of
politicians are of this kind the really
great politicians you know the true
nationalists are less than one person
unfortunately the majority of
politicians are like this they don't
really care
about the national interest or the or
the upliftment and progress of the
country and the people they just want to
come to power because power equates
power translates into money
so that's all it is politics is the
greatest and most lucrative business in
the country and that's why they will do
anything to come to power and the
easiest way is to create divisions in
society
and exploit those divisions that's just
how it works unfortunately it's it's a
it's just bad
it's it's sad but that's how it is
so that's your answer that's why they do
it
thank you sir sorry for i stopped in the
middle
not at all
always nice to talk to you thank you so
much thank you bye
okay
let us bring in
bharat hi bharat
hi sir
good evening
great fan of you
very nice to meet you very nice to meet
you what's your question sir where are
you from first of all so i'm from
baghdad that is hyderabad
all right
so i listen to your podcast as
religiously every day when i like travel
to my office
thank you so much great honor for me
so so my question is regarding cold war
era
so
we know the cold war is a
time of spice
and they even mentioned that india is a
paradise for spies
so i would like to understand
what is the role of either kgb or caa
in subverting the nation
or uh
you know
deciding what the policy that needs to
be taken by uh the government so what
was the their impact in the policy
making of our leaders
that's a good question so india see
every country in the 19
in the 20th century was essentially in
some way or the other
a plague a playground for the cold war
uh
tug of war between these two superpowers
the usa and the ussr now india was very
much a soviet satellite whether we like
it or not that that's the case during
the nerubian regime during uh because of
the policies of mr nehru and late the
later policies of the uh succeeding
regimes india was very much on the
soviet in the soviet camp not in the u.s
camp
so
there was a great deal of infiltration
there must have been some of it has been
revealed some of it has been not but
there was clearly a great deal of
infiltration of the kgb and other soviet
uh
instruments of power into the indian
administrative and governance machinery
and even in the academy academic sphere
and so on and so forth some of it has
been really revealed by us a soviet
defector to the uh to the west yuri
benjamin i believe his name was so this
has been really good
archives and so on yes so much of it has
some of it has been revealed i think
most of it has not been revealed i would
say
so we definitely certainly had that and
of course the americans would not be
would not want to be left behind so they
also infiltrated various political
parties in various parts of india
they had access to a lot of cash and
money and and therefore india's
politicians i believe to some extent
were playing both sides it's all about
money politics is always about money so
the cia was involved the kg wasn't was
involved i think the kgb's involvement
has has been revealed to a greater
extent than the involvement of the cia
but clearly the cia also had a great
deal of
of uh
you could say influence in india because
see when this uh
when the bhopal gas disaster happened
which was a crime against humanity the
indian government allowed
the the the guy who was running the show
warren anderson i believe his name was
he should have been arrested on the spot
but he was allowed to quietly slip out
of india and obviously there is a great
deal of american influence in in this
because he was an american citizen u.s
citizen the company union carbide was a
u.s company so this is just one example
of how the kind of influence even the
americans had
at the highest levels of the indian
government
so india was very much a playground of
of spies of the intelligence agencies
etc of both the superpowers india was
very deeply infiltrated by both the
sides
and so that's how it's been because see
the politicians in the past have never
cared about the national interest it was
all about staying in power clinging to
power and making money and that's how it
how the game was played in those days
you had so many scams india's defense
industry was never allowed to take off
even though we had
developed a fighter aircraft like the
marut which was a world-class fighter
aircraft etc but because these foreign
powers
convinced our politicians
that don't develop your arms industry
just buy weapons from us and we will
give you
uh
a certain percentage of the deal and so
on so you so clearly this cannot happen
just by a politician coming to india and
talking to you it happens through covert
means so
for that you need uh organs of
intelligence like the cia the kgb and so
on so that's why india was buying
weapons from
russia to a great extent india also
bought weapons from the west
to us to a lesser extent like the bow
force uh
howitzers
we bought certain aircraft from
france we had the jaguar aircraft i
believe and so on so forth so there's
always been a significant infiltration
of india's
governance and other
systems by
spies from various countries i'm sure
there are there have been pakistani and
chinese pies also in india but that that
has not been revealed to a large extent
i'm sure these games are still being
played
as we speak and such is the case always
so that's a little about that very
interesting question that's something we
have not covered i think before
yeah right
thank you so much thank you for your
question thanks bye-bye
all right
who else do we have here
who has been waiting for a long time
has anybody been waiting for a long time
i'm not sure
okay let me bring in
aditya
hello nice to meet you hello nice to
meet you nice to meet you where are you
from sir
yes sir i am
[Music]
beautiful place beautiful place very
nice very nice so so what's your
question sir yes sir my question was sir
many days ago sir i was watching some
documentaries in the in a youtube
channel services i feel trustworthy so
there it was saying about relations
between ancient persian culture and the
vedic culture sir so can you elaborate
in uh elaborate on it so because i have
also noticed like they were saying in
the nama which is their greatest epic
there are many similarities to that of
the krishna story that we do have and
there are a lot of words that we have
similar then one more uh uh question in
that same category that uh why did they
invert like they are having avura master
which is like asura or s is replaced
with h and sir then they say that they
was a rejected god sir so please
fantastic question very nice question
i'm glad that at this age you are
showing an interest in these deep topics
very interesting so let me explain what
is the relation between ancient india
and ancient persia because as you say
there is a great deal of commonality in
the foundational stories in the culture
in the language and so on so let's talk
about language first for for instance
like you said the ancient persian
language was very much
very very very similar to the ancient
sanskrit language you just replace
certain pronunciations with a different
pronunciation instead of sir you say ha
and it becomes ancient persian so
instead of saraswati you say
right and and so on so s becomes h and
that was more or less it so it was just
like a dialect of sanskrit
uh
so that's what ancient persian language
was now when it comes to the sahana if
you look at the uh if you study if you
read the shahnamah if you look at the
legend of the foundation the very first
kings of iran
they are the same kings and the same
people that are mentioned in the rig
veda in the foundational story of the
rigveda right so you have the same
foundational myths the same uh ancient
kings that are depicted in the shanama
so it's clear that the iranians and the
indians were the same people at one
point in time the persians were clearly
the same as the indians
and so so why is it why is it that way
so what happened was that at some point
in time there was a migration out of
india
and this they went westwards and they
settled in persia the ancient capital of
persia was parshwapur which is now known
as parship persepolis right parshvapur
the the clan the rigvedic or or
post-rigvedic clan of ancient indians
that went westward and settled in persia
was called the parshwa clan the parshwa
people and this
name of the clan was given eventually it
became the name of the land it became
persia right and the capital city was
persepolis which is part
and so on the language is the ancient
persian language was almost the same as
sanskrit later it diverged slowly right
so even today today's persian language
the parsi language the iranian language
it is quite similar to
to indian languages i have known
people from iran who have stayed in
india for a year or two they picked up
hindi very easily
and they speak hindi just like natives
you know so it tells you about the
closeness
linguistically of the of the two
languages
so the persons the ancient persians
where the descendants of a of an uh of
ancient indians not the other way around
and they they are not the descendants of
some aryan invasion into india and
persia it wasn't it was a number of
successive waves of migrations out of
india westwards and northwards and
persia was one of the places that was
settled by
these or one of these waves of of
migration and the language is very
similar for instance we say chandra they
say chand
right uh there is this uh this ancient
uh iranian persian hero called
right
uh so harshad is supposed to be uh
he is supposed to represent the sun
horus so let me tell you the origin of
the name khorashed and there is another
name called jamashad also right jamshed
so in
in the ancient mythology
you uh in sanskrit
what was it like
in sanskrit the name of the sun the word
for sun is swar
swara means the sun and the word kshait
means shining so when you say
swaraksheth it means
shining sun
so this term swarakshith got transformed
into corsaid so if you ask the people of
iran what is the meaning of the name
kosher they'll say it is the sun
right the word the name
means the sun in ancient in the persian
culture so that's the same as
swaraksheth of in sanskrit similarly
the son the firstborn son
of the great sun god was yama he was the
first human being yama
right and because he was the son of
surya of swar so yama was also very
shining so he was called yamaksheth
shining yama
and that became jamshed in persian
right
so you can see the similarities from
these little anecdotes from these little
vignettes of knowledge
so
the the fact of the matter is that the
persians are the descendants of ancient
indians the home of the indo-iranians
and the indo-european peoples is ancient
india
it's very ancient
and that's why
these similarities exist and
nowhere else
got interested in this topic so because
one day i was searching about zoroasters
as we were
sanskrit so then i listened to some
hymns of their uh and their cultures
that they also worship fire like us and
their pronunciation
is
yellow camel or golden camel or perhaps
old camel right so it's a sanskrit name
now he created he he proclaimed himself
as the
as the guy who has received some wisdom
from god and he inverted the the
the
morality so the devas became kind of
evil and the asuras became kind of good
in india the devas are kind of better
and the
kind of have a negative slightly
negative connotation so he inverted that
and yet the truth is that zoroastrianism
is not a monotheistic religion it is
very much a polytheistic religion just
like hinduism and that is something
people try to hide from us you know so
yeah it's a very fascinating topic the
ancient relations between india ancient
persia everything came from india
zarathustra was born a hindu because he
is the one who started zoroastrian
zoroastrianism so he came up with this
idea so they were all hindus they were
all indians they all have the same
culture it changed over time right so
great question aditya wonderful nice
talking to you thank you so much thank
you
thank you
thank you thank you bye-bye
all right whom shall we bring in
whom shall we bring in
let us bring in
kumar
hello kumar
uh hello sir very good evening to you
nice meeting you where are you from
i'm from paradisa
so what's your question
yes sir sir first of all sir if you
allow me to rectify one factual mistake
that you uh have been while answering oh
please
thank you very much sir so kind of you
so actually it was
mirage aircraft that we have brought
from france in the early 1980s it was
not jaguar
jaguar was european origin mainly based
on united kingdom
fantastic thank you so much
actually jaguar is an anglo-french
aircraft so it is french as well
let me tell you that
all right
yes so my question is regarding the nri
community uh as an indian despite having
a large presence of nri community
throughout the world
but unlike the jewish or chinese in
certain extent we are not able to
influence the global narratives and
apart from that and would should we
celebrate the success of our nri
community because to an extent i believe
it promotes brain drain
what is your take on this
so it's a good question i think i have
answered this before i mean people ask
me about uh people like kamala kamala
harris and uh
sorry sundar pichai and so on and so
forth i mean does their success have any
positive effect effect on india and
clearly it does not because it doesn't
contribute anything to india right and
they
are contributing to the success of the
united states end of the west i mean
google has no pro india policies
whatsoever despite mr sundar pichai
being their
boss and so on right
now the nri community
as opposed to the global jewish diaspora
contributes very little to india either
geopolitically or strategically or in
any other way or if you take in into
account the chinese diaspora they are
very much pro-china pro-ccp policies and
so on but in india it's not the case so
there are a couple of reasons for that
first of all when it comes to the jewish
community uh judaism is a very uh
it's a monotheistic religion uh it's a
kind of compared to a polytheistic
religion like what we call hinduism
judaism is very monochromatic and it's
very very clear clearly focused on the
national interest of israel
and therefore the entire jewish
community has a very strong interest
in the national in
furthering promoting the national
interest of israel when it comes to
india we are a very divided nation we we
don't even have a concept of nation
we don't even have the concept of the
national interest if i ask somebody on
the street what is india's national
interest they have absolutely zero idea
and we don't have a strong sense of
community there is no
common thread that seems to bind india
together and therefore when indians go
abroad they simply drift off into their
own orbit and they try to assimilate and
mix in with whatever country
they have settled in and they try to
contribute to their country only and
they feel a sense of alienation towards
india which is not the case in the case
uh in the in in the instance of israel
or china two examples so that's the
reason because we don't have any strong
common thread that binds us together our
constitution is a foreign constitution
it doesn't give you a sense of identity
of being indian
what if i ask somebody what does it mean
to be indian i will get a thousand
different answers and none of them
will will have something in common with
each other so these are the reasons this
is the challenge that india faces
together we have been bound together as
a nation state even though in the past
we used to be a civilization state in
which we had something common that bound
us all together despite living in so
many different parts of the world and
having so many differences in in
language
and
traditions and all that and still we had
something in common in the past today we
don't have it have that we have been
defined in
a way that doesn't give us anything in
common so that's the reason why indians
and nris don't really contribute
anything to us they try to escape from
india because india actually doesn't
give anything to india citizens
there is so much scarcity in india they
don't get enough jobs and if you get a
job you're treated very poorly the
government treats you terribly you pay
taxes but you don't get good roads you
don't get good conditions you get
harassment all the time from the
authorities so everybody wants to leave
india and people think that it's because
of india's culture that it is like this
it's not the case it's because of
india's governance system which is a
parasitic rent-seeking system that's why
india is in such a bad shape so so the
thing is that nris go out and live
abroad to escape these conditions in
india
so yeah it does contribute to the brain
brain drain and the solution is to
reform india it's it's not it's not the
fault of the nris right
right
that's the answer that's your answer yes
yes sir so if you allow me i would like
to add a metaphor
uh about your affair sorry the mirage
and jaguar
thing that i have pointed out please
please yeah yes sir thank you very much
while the development phase the france
update opted out of the jaguar project
in the last stage so jaguar is not
fundamentally a french thing it's more
of a british thing and to and it is uh
to counter it they
created their own
mirage program
thank you very much for this information
thank you all right nice talking to you
okay
yeah bye
all right
who else do we have
hello panu
hello sir sir i'm very no
yes i've appeared
so i'm very happy that you remember me
i yeah i think i've seen you last time
as well right yes i was the first person
awesome awesome so wherever you from
so i'm from jammu and kashmir
ah yes yes yes i do recall now yes so
what's your question
so uh can you tell me about baba raval
and uh
okay good question paparazzi was a
rajput
king i think who resisted the turkic
invasions of india
so i believe there is some kind of
legendary story uh
about him uh because historians have
once again not really researched uh or
given us any information
uh any concrete information about baba
raval so whatever we know about him is
through these semi-legendary stories
about him so one of the stories that i
heard or read about so a long time ago
is that baba rawal was some kind of
some kind of a brigand of some kind
right and he used to get into fights
with lots of people and so on and that
that's why he was asked to leave his
hometown and so on
and he he built up a
kingdom of sorts um
he had a lot of followers were all
rajputs
and he met this
he met this religious spiritual leader
called baba gorakhnat
who told him that
there is this terrible invasion of india
that's happening in the northwest of
india it is from the turks in
present-day pakistan afghanistan etc so
he exhorted him to go with his uh with
his followers
and fight of this invasion so paparazz
did that
he went to punjab
and he fought the turks he defeated them
got rid of them expelled them from india
and he was able to
delay the turkic invasions of india for
a significant period of time and he
founded a city in punjab which is now
known as rawalpindi this is the town of
ravel right
and eventually after he returned back to
his ho to to the hin to the heartland of
india
then they went northwards into northern
india into the himalayan regions the
foothills of the himalayas
and they settled down there baba rawal
and his followers and because they were
followers of baba gorak not
that's why their their descendants are
called the gorkhas
so that is the legendary story that i
have heard of course there is very
little factual information available
because we have lost our sources and our
historians have done no real research
but that's the the the mythical not the
mythical but semi-legendary story i've
heard i'm not saying he's a mythological
character he is very much a historical
character and a very significant
historical character somebody who really
fought for india
and uh
repelled the turkic invasions of india
so a very significant character but i
think we need significantly more
historical research into his life and
times and into the great deeds that he
did for the country so very interesting
question
thank you all right
thank you thank you nice to see you
again thank you bye yes good night sir
good night good night
all right who else do we have
i can see
siddharth siddharth is raising zan let
me bring in hi
hi sir can you hear me
i can hear you yes sir where are you
from
sir
well well well today we have lots of
people from horizon so nice to see that
so nice to see them what's your question
so which form of power is more powerful
is the political power or the money
power or any other form of power
and especially in our country
that's a very good question power is the
same throughout the world throughout the
world power is the same thing
so i would say that real power political
power always trumps wealth
money is not power money is something
that buys you things
but let me explain the difference
between power and money
wealth means you have a lot of money
you're able to access a lot of money and
you can buy things and so on
power is something else entirely power
means you have 100 soldiers heavily
armed soldiers
at your disposal who will obey you
instantaneously without question and do
whatever you say that is called real
power and all political power
is derived from actual
street power in that manner if you look
at the political parties in india
they all have
foot soldiers who can go out in the
streets and shut down an entire city at
home at a moment's notice
that is where actual political power
comes from because they have an army of
people you could say some some of these
political parties i'm not naming any
political party by the way there are
hundreds of political parties in this
country so i'm just talking in general
not just india but across the world
real political power comes out of this
sort of power now outside
said that
political power flows out of the barrel
of a gun yeah yeah right
yeah so in politics unless you have an
army of foot soldiers who are willing to
do
willing to obey you instantaneously and
do whatever you say unless you have that
you don't really have political power
and therefore when people say that this
person should start a political party i
mean you don't have the funds so so
that's where funding comes in if you
want to maintain an army of people like
that
then you need funds so yes money does
contribute to some extent to this but
you can raise an army of people without
money too
if you have the charisma and the
leadership qualities you know something
like idle it's a conflict
sorry
something like ideology
yes if you have the ideology and you can
uh
bring people over to your ideology
convince them and and show that you are
a leader that you should that people
should follow and so on then you can
build the political movement out of it
of course it is quite difficult that's
why we have uh so little of that
happening but that is power
real power is just the number of people
who are willing to obey you
instantaneously without question there
is a difference between influence and
power
for instance let's say you are a person
uh with a million followers on twitter
and when you say something your
followers are willing to listen to you
and they may perhaps take you seriously
or they may not perhaps take you
seriously maybe they are following you
because you are entertaining or maybe
they are following you because you have
something really interesting to say but
there is merely influence they will not
obey you without question and
instantaneously so that is influence
power is you actually own an army of
people who will follow you and obey you
instantaneously so that is the very
fundamental uh definition of power how
many people are willing to follow you
and obey you instantaneously at what
scale at what scale can you project that
power you know so that's what it is
so you mentioned previously that power
translate into wealth but how how can
that happen like
in india like this
of course if you have
if you have a thousand people willing to
follow you in and and do whatever you
say you can use them to extort the
entire population of a city
that's that's how simple it is have you
heard of haftavasuli come on my friend
wake up
add two and two together it's all right
there right in front of you if you have
an army of people who will do what you
say you can extort as much money as you
want you can come to political power you
can become
some
mp or mla or whatever or something
higher than that and once you are in
that position you can extract even more
power uh extra even more money so that
is the relationship between power and
money right very simple got it yes i got
it thank you sir
all right very nice talking to you good
question thank you bye
okay who else do we have i can see
divyang let me bring in divyang good
evening sir
i can't hear you
oh sorry
very happy to see you as well where are
you from sir so i am from uh india but i
am currently working in
miami florida
awesome awesome so it must be morning
for you right yeah it's close to noon
12.
all right all right so what's your
question sir
first of all very happy to see you all
these young people and kids on your
channel so your noble course is going in
very good direction
thank you thank you
yes only the question is uh do we have a
really track on our old uh
the text the vedas and uh puranas
means i i don't know i have have read
read somewhere or
heard somewhere that all original texts
are in germany so
this is something like that
oh so i haven't yeah first of all good
question what about the original texts
so i haven't heard that the original
texts are in germany there is no one
original text what we find is that there
are many ancient temples which which
have these palm leaf manuscripts and
many of these manuscripts are have not
been studied at all and many of them are
gathering dust so there are many
original texts right there
and some of them are there they have
been studied and
the asi and some other organs of the
government are trying to digitize them
or preserve them but i think more than
95 of these ancient manuscripts have not
been
uh preserved they have not even been
examined so i think even though we lost
the vast majority of our texts in the
destruction of our universities and
libraries a thousand years ago still
many of the temples that survived these
destruction they actually do preserve
and they still do contain many of these
ancient texts for instance the
arthashastra was rediscovered in this
manner because uh one of these ancient
manuscripts was the arthashastra so
so what what has been what happened is
that these texts the vedas etc they were
written very very very long ago
and they were passed on orally
by rote memorization by precise
memorization
so and this can this tradition continue
generation after generation for very
very long time for many thousands of
years and eventually maybe around 2000
or so years ago some people actually
wrote it down and that's how it was
preserved in the physical form and then
many copies were made
and many temples
had these copies and similarly for the
rama and the mahabharata if you go to
thailand or cambodia or whatever they
have their own versions of the ramayana
which they have also preserved for many
many generations for more than thousand
two thousand years possibly possibly
so i would say that i don't know about
the german uh i'm sure even the germans
uh
have some original text which they may
have taken from india because the
germans were very much interested in
indology and sanskrit because sanskrit
is in some ways quite similar to the
german language in terms of the kind of
sandi structure we have in sanskrit and
the grammatical structure we have so the
germans were very much interested in
sanskrit you had german philosophers who
were deeply influenced by the upanishads
and the vedas and so on scupenhauer is
one example
so it's possible like you said that some
original texts may currently be in
germany but i think we have way more
original texts in india and we have not
even studied them examined them carbon
dated them to see how old they were and
how long ago they were written but i
think that the majority of whatever is
has survived is still in india and i
hope that the government does show some
initiative in preserving them and
digitizing them so that we don't lose
whatever knowledge we still have so the
gita pressing guru for they do have
many uh
ori means the tax i believe but they are
out of funding or very low funding i
believe
yes the gita press has done a very very
important uh
they have played a very important role
in preserving many of our ancient
texts they have uh published versions of
their version of the mahabharata
ramayana the gita etc etc
and many texts that people are not
really aware of so they have done that
but unfortunately it's not very well
funded we have all these
we have all kinds of unnecessary things
being funded but something as valuable
as the gita press which is doing such
incredible and important work is not
getting enough funding so that's the
tragedy of modern india right and i hope
the situation changes because the
government has the funds the power to do
to to change everything if they want
yeah right that's what i was about to
say that instead of funding the pharma
agitation and the ceo
we should uh you know fund this type of
but thank you very much for taking my
question maybe i'll ask more question
next time
thank you so much very nice to meet you
thank you thank you bye bye
okay
whom shall we bring in
many people are raising their hands
hello
hi can you see me
sir i am honored to talk to you sir
very nice to talk to you where are you
from
sir i am right now in punjab
my father is an army he is an army
officer awesome awesome salute to your
father sir
thank you sir so so my question is that
uh how can we uh remove democracy like
the
present fake democracy and instead
implement the democracy which was used
in ancient india so and also how can
do we have to point guns at the national
politicians or uh which countries would
resist our
motion against the fake democracy which
is controlled by the britishers
which is
indirectly controlled by the britishers
so how can we do that
right i i am very much against pointing
guns at anybody so we need to uh you
know
we we need to consider uh alternatives
to that so the first thing is that uh we
need to ensure that everybody in india
understands that the constitution that
we are currently following has been
imposed upon us undemocratically since
we are talking about democracy the
constitution should be uh
should come into force in a democratic
manner let me give you an example let's
talk about the u.s constitution when the
americans won their war of independence
their so-called founding fathers drafted
a constitution for their country it is
about seven pages long and then this
constitution was put to a vote
which means that the entire country was
asked those who were eligible to vote
white men only but whatever so they were
asked whether they are
willing to accept the constitution or
not yes or no it's called a referendum
so the constitution was put to a
referendum and when the majority of
those who are eligible to vote they
approved the constitution only then did
it become binding on the country so it
was
brought to power
brought into effect through a democratic
vote through a referendum now when it
comes to india
the constituent assembly of india
was undemocratic in its very genesis it
did not represent the people of india it
was a people who were a bunch of people
who were hand-picked uh who were elected
through an election that
that involved the participation of about
only 13 percent of the eligible
population of india and many of the
people of the constituent assembly were
actually hand-picked they were members
of prison nominees of princely states
and so on and so forth so first of all
the constituent assembly that drafted
the constitution did not represent the
will of the people of india secondly
after the constitution was drafted
and created they put we the people of
india on it
but it was not put to a vote the people
of india were not given the opportunity
to either accept it or reject it it was
just imposed upon us by force and that
is the constitution we are forced to
follow today and all our laws all our
hindu phobic laws all all of it comes
from there and of course the majority of
the laws are still
left over from the retrieved regime from
the british occupation of india so if
the people of india understand this fact
if they come
if they first of all people don't even
know this
they think that the constitution
represents our will
and the so-called drafters of the
constitution where people who
represented the will of the people of
india which is the lie
so this knowledge
is not known to 99 of the people of
india
right
and unless it is known people will not
wake up so first the first step is that
people need to know this that the
constitution is an illegitimate
undemocratically imposed constitution
and secondly once they know this then
they need to put pressure on the
politicians
to change it
because if the constitution is
illegitimate and undemocratic it has to
be changed in a democratic manner so we
need a new constituent assembly to draft
a new constitution and then we will have
real democracy if it is a properly done
constitution
in a democratic process then we will
actually possibly have a true democracy
we will have a new constitution that
reflects our cultural and civilizational
values not western values right
so that's what needs to happen pointing
guns at people is counterproductive it's
going to invite retaliation from the
state and that's never going to help
anyone but it has to be done in this
manner spread the knowledge
spread the fact that the constitution is
illegitimate and undemocratic that's the
first step we need to do
right
sir in earlier podcast uh you have also
mentioned that there are there are
countries who will resist uh the uh
right now current government uh
uh intentions to make a hindu raster
yeah so what uh who are those countries
and why
they would resist this kind of motion
which would happen in india
it's the western world they want their
their system of governance their system
of values to be spread all across the
world right so today we are following
western values in the western system of
governance and they want this uh
this system
to spread worldwide and they don't want
it to be removed from any country
the moment somebody goes against the
west you know what happens to them
there's a regime change attempt and all
that which we which we see everywhere
for instance saddam hussein was part of
the western machinery but eventually
when he did something that they did not
like they removed him and so on and so
forth so if uh right now there are
countries like russia
which follow their own system iran which
follows its own system uh china which
follows its own system
and the west doesn't like that they are
trying to undermine these countries i'm
not saying we should support china but
i'm just giving an example so the moment
india tries to do that they are coming
to try and undermine us as well the west
is all powerful right now but things are
changing so india needs to bide its time
and do it when the time is right that's
your answer sir
yes sir thank you sir
thank you so much nice talking to you
bye
okay uh
everyone's raising their hands
hello hi sandeepan
yes hi hi sir
where are you from sir
i am from kolkata
kolkata very nice very nice been there
long ago so what's your question sir
so my question is that i have made a lot
of i have studied with lot of people
from the west
and i have come to realize that they are
not as smart as indian means from my
limited experience that i have
so my question is that is it a true
assumption or is it can it be proved
genetically that we indians are the
uh
are the most intelligent people when it
comes to mathematics at least
and
means yeah so that was that was my
question
okay okay very nice question very good
question so the answer uh is something
like this
i think that people
the world over
are more or less the same actually
but cultures and civilizations are
different
so if you take the average individual
anywhere in the world their level of
intelligence will depend on mostly the
kind of nutrition they had
through the childhood so people who are
malnourished or who went through poverty
and therefore they did not get
sufficient nutrition their iq level will
be low unfortunately so that is one
thing that that is found across the
world so there are places in sub-saharan
africa where the overall average iq is
low now people like nasim nicholas talib
say that iq itself is a
pseudo-scientific swindle and it does
not take everything into account overall
intelligence and so on
so what i would say is that i would not
say that it's a genetic thing that some
people are more intelligent some are
less intelligent i would say it's a
cultural and civilizational thing so if
you look at the history of the past 10
000 years of the world you will see that
india was the most technologically
scientifically advanced civilization in
human history all of mathematics
astronomy everything came out of india
we have the oldest evidence of
astronomical observations in the world
we the first recorded evidence of a
supernova which is from about 5500 bce
from northern india kashmir and
mathematics developed in india calculus
trigonometry infinite series everything
developed in india it was later
appropriated by the west ayurveda
pharmacology toxicology uh astronomy
navigation so many sciences everything
developed in india in the in the uh
hindu phase of our civilization we had
extremely advanced uh architecture town
planning we had a standardization of
weights and measures
and uh if you look at our ancient
literature we seem to have figured out
the speed of light several thousand
years ago and so on so
civilizationally we were able to create
an environment for a very long period of
time in which this the pursuit of pure
knowledge was not just encouraged it was
it was regarded as the highest ideal and
the in the highest thing one can pursue
in la in in one's human existence so it
is a cultural and civilizational thing
that indians always produce the greatest
thinkers the greatest philosophers the
greatest mathematicians the greatest
scientists and so on so i think i would
i would not say that it's a genetic
thing that indians
possibly may be superior to people from
other parts of the world in terms of
intellect i think uh
it's a cultural and uh civilizational
thing if you create the right sort of
environment then even the most average
person
will be uh motivated
to pursue knowledge and to try and seek
and try and contribute some some kind of
uh advancement in knowledge to humanity
so i think it's a cultural and
civilizational thing and unfortunately
we have lost that right now so we need
to rebuild that you know
so so if it is a cultural thing but we
started it first right so why why the
western people couldn't start it
before us we are the ones who
who started uh the
hindu hindu culture such a complicated
culture that we have started why they
couldn't start before us because we had
the culture that promoted
such uh such pursuits pursuit of
knowledge percent of excellence it is
something that uh was built over a very
long period of time maybe ten thousand
years or more and that was preserved in
other parts of the world maybe we did
not have the kind of climate that we had
here so that we could live this peaceful
life and we could build the large cities
right in in europe for instance you have
a very different climate it's very cold
and it's it's hard to live to build
large civilizations
unless you're the 21st century or 20th
century
and we know that people who lived in
other parts of the world
lived rather primitive lives i would not
use it as a
say this in terms of a value judgment
it's merely an observation
that people in other parts of the world
lived rather primitive lives compared to
the great civilization in the saraswati
sindhu region and the rest of india
so if you live a life that is fraught
with danger in which you have
in which you have
fights and clashes with other tribes and
all that and if you don't have a settled
system of agriculture and all those
things then you are not going to be able
to develop any culture or knowledge or
science or philosophy i mean if you if
you don't know whether you'll be alive
tomorrow or not you will not be able to
think philosophical thoughts right so
that's the kind of system we had it was
a very peaceful
culture and civilization for many
thousands of years i mean there's this
article in the new scientist that says
that the indus valley region seems to
have had a complete absence of warfare
for a very long period of time so these
are the reasons these are the factors
that create an environment that is
conducive
to the
uh intellectual uh thought process and
that's why we had that
yeah thank you thanks a lot sir for that
thanks for your question very
interesting question
thank you thank you bye-bye
okay let's take some more questions do
we have anybody okay here we have mr
akshay khabra hi
hello sir how are you
i'm very well how are you doing where
are you from
uh so i'm from udaipur rajasthan
very nice very nice what's your question
uh so sir uh i want to ask you
recently in china there was an article
trended from their media house named
soho
about the chinese expansion in till 2050
so do you believe that china can take
over after
do you believe in this theory that china
can do this thing by 2050
uh i think that if the chinese are
allowed
first of all it's about what we allow
them to do and secondly it's about what
they are capable of doing
if they are able to sustain the economic
growth that they would like to see then
they will have the resources to build up
a very powerful military
and they certainly are an expansionist
uh
nation the chinese communist party
envisages complete global
hegemony across the world they want to
recreate a middle kingdom counter kind
of thing in which china is the center of
the universe and everybody comes and
pays tribute to the chinese and it is
the only large power in the world all
other powers are either small or
completely fragmented or weak
so they would like to see
india to be broken up into pieces they
would like to see parts of india be
absorbed into china like arunachal
pradesh
and they would like to see india broken
up into north south east west all that
they are they have been fermenting
problems in india for a very long period
of time since the 1950s 60s in
kashmir in the northeast of india so yes
they definitely have this sort of agenda
they have this dream
of taking the taking over the world they
also have unfinished business with the
russians they almost went to war with
russia in the 1960s russians the ussr
almost
nuked china which it almost came to that
they had a territorial dispute for a
very long time which was settled in the
1990s and 2000s i believe
so that is something the chinese haven't
forgotten where as they grow more
powerful they will want to reclaim that
territory also from the russians or to
claim it to claim it and so on
so
the chinese uh
the rise of china is not a peaceful rise
they want to take over first of all
first of all they want to take back
taiwan like everybody knows and once
that happens they will want to take over
other parts like arunachal pradesh and
so on and they will want to fragment
india so i believe that they are very
serious about this they have been
writing about this for for a very long
time unfortunately most of the writings
most of the publications are in the
chinese language and since in india we
have not developed this scholarship in
the chinese language so that we
understand them that's why we don't
really know about it but the west has
been studying this
there has been
about 20 years ago there was this book
this publication called unrestricted
warfare by a couple of chinese military
officers which speaks about all these
things about militarizing
uh law militarizing other things as well
and
using a system of uh complete warfare
and so on so the chinese have had these
this agenda for a very long time so we
have to take it seriously the question
is will they be able to sustain
the growth that has led them to where
they are today because right now the
chinese economy seems to be floundering
it seems to be under recession uh the
numbers that are coming out of china say
that there's about five or six percent
growth but the actual figures may
maybe one or two percent only or even
less than that because you cannot really
trust the chinese numbers
so if that is the case then the chinese
economy is stagnating and there that
could be actually a problem for the
world because it may
make the chinese communist party a
little desperate and they will try and
grab whatever they can right now so that
is a possibility but the chinese have
the agenda for sure to rule the entire
world so we have to take it very
seriously and we have to develop our own
strength
so that that doesn't happen
right
so do you believe that china is still
playing that divide and rule card in
india
absolutely it's always done that it will
always do that
no question about it it is doing that
yes
because as you know
many indian political parties
have certain kinds of agreements etc
with the chinese whether it's the indian
communist party or some other parties
and so on so yeah
that divide and rule is very much there
there there they will keep on doing that
so we have to be
on the alert and we have to be aware of
their agenda right
okay thank you sir
thank you so much nice talking to you
nice speaking to you bye
okay let us bring in swati good evening
hello good evening sir
good evening swathi where are you from
sir first
so first of all i would like to tell you
that i am a science student and uh in a
million of years i would have never
thought that i would love history
history was one of the subjects that i
hated the most during my school years
but for the past one year
just because of you and your podcast
i have fallen love i fall in love with
history and thank you thank you so much
sir for that
my pleasure my pleasure thank you so
much
so so my question to you is that um we
have read we have listened to it many
times that uh in our epics in our texts
many ashudiyas have crept in there are
certain editions that have been done to
our epics and just because uh now it is
thousands of years old stories and
and we don't know sanskrit that much so
sir how can we
uh you know decipher that this isn't a
shuddhi this is an edition because many
a times we hear that uttar ramayana is
actually not a part of the original
valmiki ramayana
so such type of asunas how can we
decipher it on our own
we cannot do it to the complete extent
because we don't have the different
editions and versions of these texts
chronologically so in let's say that it
was written
just hypothetically let's say the ramen
was returned 5000 years ago
hypothetically and then if we
i'm gonna mute you
okay so hypothetically let's say it was
written uh five thousand six thousand
years ago and let's say we have all the
editions of the ramayana edition one two
three four five in case we have that
then we can see what additions and what
uh modifications were done and in that
case we will be able to tell which is
the original version but unfortunately
we don't have that
most of our ancient texts got burned in
those
turkic invasions of india so whatever
little we have we have to treat it as a
great treasure and unfortunately we will
not be able to tell what changes what
modifications or deletions if any
happened at what period in time
so unfortunately what we have now is
what we have and we have to treat it
as the
as the sacred text we do know that lots
of changes have happened over time
because there are versions of the
ramayana in other countries southeast
asia thailand cambodia indonesia bali
etc in which you have different versions
of these stories we have certain
embellishments we have certain new
characters small minor characters that
are that are added to it for instance
there is a version of the ramayana in
which there is this mermaid who meets
lord hanuman during the passage to sri
lanka
to lanka and he actually marries this
mermaid and so on which is not there in
the original ramayana in india so this
is an addition that has been done in
another version of the ramayana and so
on so forth so there are many such local
versions of the ramayana which have
slightly different tales and all that
unfortunately there is no way of knowing
which are they or these which are the
additions which is the actual original
text there is no way of knowing it
unfortunately so what we have to do
is we have to preserve all these
different versions of the texts and we
have to regard the all of them as the
sacred text that's the only thing we can
do right now
right
so sir thank you so much for your answer
and so there's just one more suggestion
that i have for your webinar um
many many times you have told that we
need india as a country needs a dharmic
constitution so sir if you can make a
little bit of webinar what will be the
dharmic constitution or what changes we
can make in the present constitution to
make it a little dharmic so it will be a
very helpful for all of us i guess
thank you thank you for the suggestion
thank you so much
all right thank you thank you for the
question
thank you bye
all right
whom shall i bring in
that i have not spoken to earlier
let me bring in
very nice to meet you where are you from
sir
maharashtra
very nice okay what's your question sir
so my question is uh can anyone write
research paper on history or any
institutional background required for
them
and how to start itself
so i think i don't think any
institutional background is required to
write a research paper in history what
you have to do is you need to have
sufficient knowledge about the topic
that you're writing about and you need
to know how to write a research paper
what are the what what
things are needed you need to obviously
be able to cite
sources original sources
and proper sources and you need to be
able to structure your argument and your
paper properly if you do that if it is a
high quality research you can submit it
to any reputed or or official research
journal
and you you don't need to be affiliated
with any institution for that you can do
it even if you are unaffiliated even if
you are an independent researcher
right so as long as you know how to
write a proper research paper and as
long as your research paper is high
quality and it's original you should
have no issue
in being able to get your work published
in a research journal
right
so actually it belongs to arya community
but many people from uh south india they
belong they believe that
they are not hindus they are gravity
so i really want to
write something on that topic or do
something
that is great that is great so i think
you should go ahead and do that and uh
as long as your argument is good as long
as the paper is well written and it has
sufficient sources etc as required then
i don't think there should be any
problem in you submitting and having a
research paper on this particular
subject published
right so so it's a it's a it's great to
see that you you have this motivation to
do that
so go ahead and do it i would say do it
thank you thank you
thank you so much thank you nice meeting
you bye-bye
pranav
hello
hello sir good evening am i audible sir
yes your audible yes
sir i'm a huge fan of your work and how
much information you are actually
disseminating to the general audience
i'm from kerala
and uh mike i have so many questions to
you i wish i had a podcast or something
so i could
ask everything but i know
i'll have to ask only one question
my question is sir in even though i'm
not so widely read in the vedas and
associated things they talk about a
substance called soma
and this substance apparently uh was
supposed to be ingested by the priest
during rituals and
uh i'm wondering whether this substance
is some kind of hallucinogen or is it
comparable to all these shamanistic
rituals where they use
uh stuff like ayahuasca and all in south
american jungles and whether this
actually produces some kind of altered
state of consciousness
which uh helps in may maybe perceiving
the world a little differently or in a
more pacifistic way which may help us to
enlighten ourselves
what is your take on this
whether whether such substances were
used or whether they were not
whether they were like
decried by the ancient vedic community
that's a very good question very
interesting question soma what is the
what what exactly is soma unfortunately
today we have lost the identity of this
harp or this plant or whatever it was
now if you look at the vedas there is a
significant amount of references to the
great uh
somaras they call it sumaras
and soma the the
soma is also associated with the moon
that's why they called monday so
right monday is the day of moon
in in french it's called landi which is
the day of the loon which is the moon
so in french it is the moon day in
english it is the moon day and in in
sanskrit it is
again associated with the moon that's
very interesting now uh somaras is
associated is believed
if you look at the depictions and the
way it is described in the vedas it is
said that the great warrior indra
before going to battle would drink lots
of somaras because it gave him a lot of
strength and energy and the vigor to
fight in the battle so
that tells me that it's not a
hallucinogenic uh compound or or
substance because if you are intoxicated
and you go to war you're gonna lose your
head right there
right so so that is a very interesting
clue in the vedas in the rigveda i
believe so it is something the warriors
would drink before going to war because
it gave them strength energy and vigor
now
the question is what is the identity of
this particular plant is it one plant is
it a mixture of plants we don't we are
not quite sure now this parsley parsees
the persons who are the descendants of
our ancient ancestors
they also
have something called yasna which is
the same thing as the yagna
and they also drink homer
they call it homa which we call soma and
the plant that they use in the the homer
ceremony is called the ephedra plant
which is kind of
it is actually a banned substance in
athletics because it is a performance in
enhancing substance it kind of gives you
some kind of performance kick
so it does seem to be in line with what
is described in the vedas that you drink
soma and you get more energy and
strength and you can go and fight a war
and actually win it
so the ephedra plant is a performance
enhancing
it has some performance enhancing
qualities it is a banned substance in
athletics and in competitions and it is
what the iranians the parsees have been
using as their homa plant
now is it the original soma plant of our
vedas we are not quite sure some
researchers have said that it is the
ephedra plant some people have said that
it is the uh
it is one of those mushrooms
those magic mushrooms kind of things uh
which could probably possibly be the
soma plant so there's a number of
theories out there unfortunately none of
these theories have been has been proven
conclusively
so
at the end of the day it is still a
question that's still open
and we still haven't completely solved
the mystery of what is the identity of
the soma plant but clearly there was
something that did exist and there was
even a depiction of the process that was
used to
extract the soma rust so you to press
the stalks of the plant and extract the
soma ross and then that's what you drank
and that's how you get got the energy so
it's one of the big mysteries
in our ancient history and it has still
not been solved it is mostly western
researchers who have been trying to
solve it indians obviously have been
sleeping all this time but i think
hopefully something will change and
maybe we'll be able to figure out what
it was
so that's a very interesting question
thanks for asking this
thank you sir thank you so much
nice meeting you thank you bye
okay sushant has been waiting very
patiently let me bring in sushant hi
sushant
uh hello sir again this is my second
time
oh it is very nice
so uh my question is uh
that uh
even uh after the colonization done by
mughals
uh essentially uh means somehow whatever
we were colonizing
our own independent empires
even though they were small
or smaller of some sorts so why weren't
we able to do the same uh when the
british colonized us
right that's a very good question so uh
the mughals were defeated conclusively
by the maratha marathons uh it started
i'm gonna mute you because it's a lot of
noise but all right so the mughals were
defeated
by the marathas by the maratha empire
eventually the maratha empire was able
to reclaim and and and
and free and liberate india from the
turkey occupation the maratha empire
went all the way up to the
two parts of afghanistan etc so all of
india was free
and unfortunately because of the
infighting between the marathas and
because of their
because a succession plan went wrong and
you had weaker leaders who came up
that's why the british were able to
defeat the
the marathas and
eventually take over india and colonize
india
so
and what the british did was what the
mughals did not do they they created
these artificial famines every year
millions of indians died in these
artificial famines because the logic was
that if the indians are so weak that
they are dying if there is no food then
how will they fight so that is one
strategy the british used
to create this large-scale
environment of starvation throughout
india which prevented indians from
fighting back still indians did fight
back like in 1857 in which the we almost
won the thing you know
but
and and after that what the british did
was that they changed the indian
education system they imposed their
colonial system on india so slowly
indians started getting brainwashed and
they started looking upon the british as
as actually good people as the superior
race
and this the indian started looking at
the british culture as superior to
indian culture and so on uh
the education was uh imposed in the
english language
indians were brainwashed indians were
portrayed as inferior and then the
british started this political movement
called the indian national congress
in which british educated people were
brought to the top and they were
portrayed as india's
national independence leaders even
though they were actually delaying
india's independence so it is this very
interesting very well thought out very
well
planned strategy of the british
that ensured that their rule lasted this
long and that's why we had such poor
leaders
and that's why we are still to a very
large extent mentally colonized so it
was a very well crafted strategy of
divide and rule and impose their foreign
culture and make indians ashamed of
their own culture
that is why
we are in the situation where we are
today
so good question
so uh yes um
i have one more question so no no i'm
sorry only one question per person very
sorry maybe next time maybe next time
okay thank you so much for the question
thank you thank you thanks for your
question bye
okay who all do we have i can see a
number of people waiting let me bring in
tamai
hello
good evening
how long do you think that
that china's
bully and conquer policy is going to
work in in the geopolitical world
and so and with the ongoing
crisis in china such as the recent power
crisis
uh is it going to add any
new tactic to its current playbook or or
other things that's going to remain the
same
okay good question very good question so
china's policy will not change they
their objectives are the same and
therefore their strategies and tactics
will evolve according to the situation's
situation but their objectives won't
change they want to become the
superpower the sole superpower in the
world they want to displace the us and
make and
essentially
uh
become the sole superpower in the world
they want to see india fragmented and
broken up they want to absorb parts of
india like pradesh and so on so their
rise is going to be
a non-peaceful rise which which the
world now knows very well
of course like you mentioned the chinese
economy does seem to be showing very
strong signs of recession it seems to be
floundering
and therefore their tactics will evolve
based on that because they need money
they they have risen to the position
they are in right now because of their
economic power so they have pursued
certain policies that gave them double
digit growth year upon year for a very
long long time and that's why their
economic might has
grown to the extent that it has today
and that is also the reason why they
have been able to build a powerful
military
now that their economy seems to be under
a recession they will perhaps become
desperate and they will perhaps try to
take over taiwan very quickly and maybe
some other military misadventures there
is a possibility
so there is the state we are in right
now so based upon how things change they
will certainly like you said
uh try to change their tactics and
strategies so if their economy doesn't
uh grow the way they want it to grow
then they may become a little desperate
and they may try to grab whatever they
can right now with the economic might
that they still have
perhaps the economy will shrink in the
future so that is a possibility so it
all depends things change and your
strategies and tactics have to adapt to
deal with the changing geopolitical and
global environment
so we are going to see changes certainly
uh it is quite likely it does look kind
of quite likely that the chinese economy
is is going to slow down
and that may actually be a bad sign for
the world right okay sir
sir and uh
do you think that
that china is is trying to target the
the big boy oil fields in in arunachal
pradesh
for its military campaigns
okay uh i'm supposed to take only one
question per person so my question is no
my question is no my answer to that
question is no yes sir all right thank
you so much thank you for your question
nice to meet you thank you so much for
for letting me ask i'm a really big fan
i've been waiting for this question to
be answered for a really long time
awesome nice meeting your friend
no
hello rahul
can you hear me
i can't hear you sir you're not audible
i cannot hear you very sorry
okay um i will take you in next time
thank you so much very sorry i could not
hear you
okay let's bring in somebody else uh who
all can i see here i will bring in mr
abhinay
hello good evening
once again i can't hear you
sorry
can't hear you
okay next time next time i'll bring in
somebody else
whom shall i bring in let me bring in
good evening
uh good evening sir
sir um
i really admire work uh you're really a
great person because of you like
several theories like arya and vision
theory which made up in our mind we got
logic and researched
uh and today we know that it's false
it's all driven nationalists you know
fall that they are dividing people
so uh so my question is
like today's indian navy as compared to
the the world's elitist naval forces is
uh you know quite
less in comparison to
uh like united states or china
but
uh in the past like if we consider the
chanakya he talked about the four kinds
of ship
then the cholas
but after the 13th century the decline
of the chola's leadership
we saw dirt for like four five centuries
and then uh in the marathas we got the
naval power on a rise so so while uh
reading about the marathas i got to know
about one of the
elitist naval admirals who has been kind
of erased from the indian history and
his name was kanhoji
so sir may you please shed some light on
his achievements
uh the great maratha admiral kanhoji
angre
okay so the thing is see i haven't
studied kanoji angry's career in great
detail i'm certainly aware of the fact
that he was one of the greatest naval
warriors of in our entire history and
you could say that he's in a way
the the
father of the indian navy because it was
during the maratha era that because of
his achievements the maratha navy was
able to expand so much it was able to
defeat the portuguese in a number of
battles and various other forces
so that's what i can tell you because i
haven't read his career in great detail
that is a very specific neat topic
my interest is kind of global so i will
not be able to give you right now
details of his exploits i know that he
was their greatest admiral he is the
father or the greatest
the greatest leader in the maratha navy
and
if i i certainly have read about it if i
recall that
he had defeated the portuguese in a
number of battles he had even inducted
some europeans as officers in the
marathon navy yes sir so yes
he inducted dutch actually
and sir there's one
yes and there was one more incident like
portuguese and english navy combined
together an attack but still they failed
twice to defeat him
yes and what i recall was that his
strategy and tactics were very
innovative he
he relied not on large ships but on
smaller and more agile ships faster
ships which were able to maneuver out
maneuver the european uh
naval ships and all that and that's why
he was able to defeat them multiple
times
and even so that he
even so that he captured the ship of the
president of the bombay presidency
so that he hcs algerian so that's why i
thought like it's very interesting to
discuss about such a naval admiral who
was like greater than the whole world's
navy combined
i absolutely agree he's one of the
greatest naval officers and greatest
naval commanders of all time in the
world and it is a really a tragedy that
we are not recognizing such incredible
heroes that we have had such great
leaders of our people and for our
country
uh even the marathas i mean compared to
the cholas etc compared to the cholas
etc the marathas have still got a little
bit more exposure in our textbooks and
yet it is not sufficient so the kind of
the way the marathas has been portrayed
is is
rather insufficient the portrait is very
insufficient and people like
angry etc don't even get a mention which
is a tragedy which needs to change
and that's why i keep saying we need to
revise and revisit our history textbooks
and decontaminate our history so it's a
very interesting
topic that you have brought forth thank
you for bringing this up
okay thank you sir
thank you very much thank you bye
okay i will have to
limit my next question to only one
person because we are reaching the end
of our thing
of tonight's session
so i can see a number of people waiting
only one will get the chance i'm very
sorry very sorry
let me bring in
let me bring in jignesh
hi
hello sir i have been a huge fan of you
i have been following your beer biceps
podcast for like so many times i listen
them twice first on youtube and then on
spotify
so i'm from 9 mumbai india and my
question is a little like a personal but
many of my students of my age have this
so i'm in my like final year of
engineering and i need to know that
whether if i go out and come back again
first hiding purpose then it will like
benefit or like harm for my country like
will it be good for brain drain or it
will be bad like if i study outside gain
some more knowledge and then come back
and be prosperous in terms of economy
rather than like
staying here
yes i get it very good question what i
would say is that you should move right
now right now you're very young
right now what you should do is you
should do what is best for you and your
personal career
so go wherever it take wherever you need
to go if you have to go abroad go abroad
get your education there i would say
that in the next 10 20 years
build a career whether it's in india
whether it's abroad wherever you can
and and become the best version of
yourself that you possibly can be try
and achieve your full potential and
later on in life maybe after your 30s or
40s at that point in time maybe if
you're abroad maybe you can come back to
india and contribute something to the
country but right now you have to focus
only on yourself
only on your personal growth because
unless you grow up into somebody
who is
who can contribute some genuine value to
the country there's no point
so right now do whatever is best for
yourself and later when you have
achieved something of significance then
you can think of contributing to the
country so that is the simple strategy
every student in the country needs to
follow right now do what is best for
yourself
yes sir so i like a small quote that you
said in the podcast like for years i
have been trying like trying to go
abroad but the quote that you said that
when a structure is about the cumberland
the rats are the first to leave the
structure so that's what made me think
whether to like stay in india and do
something good for my country rather
than glorifying the west
awesome thank you very much for the
question thanks nice meeting you
okay my friends i am very sorry i'm
gonna have to
wrap it up over here i know many of you
are waiting here i am very sorry
hopefully next time and thank you for
all to all the viewers thank you to all
of you
who joined
thank you for all the questions and i
will keep on doing this this is great
fun and i hope to meet each one of you
in the future and hopefully someday
we'll even meet in person
so
the great session wonderful
thank you so much
and i will see you again next week thank
you everybody have a good night have a
good day
until next time
bye